<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Performance Theory: Theatricality, the Anthropological Turn, the Body, and the Digital</title>
        <link>http:&#x2F;&#x2F;lachlankermode.com&#x2F;performance-theory-alpha</link>
        <description></description>
        <generator>Gutenberg</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <atom:link href="http:&#x2F;&#x2F;lachlankermode.com&#x2F;performance-theory-alpha&#x2F;rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
                <title>Local Theory</title>
                <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>http:&#x2F;&#x2F;lachlankermode.com&#x2F;performance-theory-alpha&#x2F;posts&#x2F;local-theory&#x2F;</link>
                <guid>http:&#x2F;&#x2F;lachlankermode.com&#x2F;performance-theory-alpha&#x2F;posts&#x2F;local-theory&#x2F;</guid>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Theory is a disconcerted practice for our authors this week. Jon McKenzie’s short summary of the anthropological turn recognizes that theory must dance a line between the general and the local, re-presenting a sense of each in the other:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The challenge, then, is not to abandon conceptual modelization, but rather to inscribe this movement within one’s specific situtation to fold generalization back on itself in order to avoid reducing performance to any one model.&lt;br&gt;
                        The Liminal Norm, pp.52.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This formulation is, in a sense, good theory. It suspends the explicative imperative by rolling the specifics of the process in question in a simple yet endlessly constructive gesture, namely ‘folding.’ By making this gesture reflexive, a folding of generalization back on itself, the use of theory in the local is painted as a powerfully possibly gesture that somehow resists the shortcomings of its unfolded formulation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What, though, does generalization folding back on itself actually mean? The formulation is typical of media theory (one of McKenzie’s disciplinary sympathies) in that it is both precise and vague. We can trace the phrase’s grammar without difficulty. ‘Conceptual modelization,’ a tactic of theory at large, ought to be ‘inscribed’ locally so that ‘generalization’ can be reflexivly ‘folded,’ the result being a multivalent model of performance. The air-quoted terms in this phrase, however, are necessarily and intentionally equivocal. Concepts are morphologically hypostatized so that they may be put in syntactic relationship to other concepts, and we are left with a metaphysical pattern, or, to project into three-dimensional space, a constellation, that is repeatably representative of some&#x2F;many social realities by virtue of its degree of separation from any given reality in question.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because theory mediates the space between separate entities (conceptual, physical, miscegenated), its project must be conscientious. The Western tradition of theory as it derives from the Greeks, as McKenzie notes, “presupposes a unified for while promising a single, correct answer” in framing its inquiries in the form ‘what is …?’. Both theoretically and pragmatically, anthropology is beleagured by the exacting ghosts&#x2F;skeletons of colonialism. One cannot construct a general theory without asking for and by whom was it constructed. If a theory mediates a space, then it must also construct a politics of mediation. As Schechner notes, “we need no new educating to the idea that the instruments and means of observing and recording things deeply affect what’s being observed.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is no simple matter to construct an ethical theory of interaction, observation, or representation given the century-old ossifications of racialized, gendered, Other-ated aesthetics. How does one begin to think through a set of variegated social realities, let alone represent them in one’s own social realities, let alone wearing the mantle of discipline plaited at an institution punctuated by patriarchal oversight and appropriative productivity? This is the task of the ethnographer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first point of procedure in this undertaking for Turner and Schechner is a reflexive methodology that is always partial in its approach to meaning, never total. Turner puts this elegantly:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pure anthropological functionalism, whose aim is to state the conditions of social equilibrium among the components of a social system at a given time, cannot deal with meaning, for meaning always involves retrospection and reflexivity, a past, a history. Meaning is the only category which grasps the full relation of the part to the whole in life, for value, being dominantly affective, belongs essentially to an experience in a conscious present.&lt;br&gt;
                        From Ritual to Theatre, Victor Turner.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theory mediates spaces, and thus a general theory is, in principle, a constellation that has a grammar and vocabulary for every possible space in a site. It seems highly improbable that any thinker, or body&#x2F;history of thinkers for that matter, might be able to construct an abstraction both capacious and specific enough to do justice to every instance in social reality. The first irremedial problem is language; language speaks, and any one person or scholarly tradition only ever speaks a limited number of languages. There will always be a construction that is glossed, translated, or entirely erased. When we think about languages as not only linguistic systems, but also coporeal, cultural, and other modes of affective construction, any attempt at general theory is overwhelmed by a Brobdingnagian mass of perspectives.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problematic of general theory is also true of any given local theory. From the perspective of the human mind’s processing power, even a small village’s specific cultural social reality is unfathomably data replete. Knowledge is irremediably perspectival, despite Western theory and linguism’s bad habit for proposing absolutisms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McKenzie sees Performance Studies, I think, and indeed performance itself, as a mediator in this problematic of theory. Rather than proposing alternative theories that displace and invalidate prior ones (analytic philosophy’s favorite pasttime), performance is “our rehearsal of a general theory.” Moving through Schechner, we know that the rehearsal space is a ‘betwixt and between’ where the subjunctive roams, rather than a rigid space structured by the indicative. (At least, it is this in theory!). McKenzie sees performance theories, ventriloquizing Ronald Grimes through Turner, as “dialectical dancing partners.” They are animated interlocutors that structure and restructure space, each perspectival, partial.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</description>
            </item>
        <item>
                <title>The Media Philosophy of Stanislavsi&#x27;s System</title>
                <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>http:&#x2F;&#x2F;lachlankermode.com&#x2F;performance-theory-alpha&#x2F;posts&#x2F;media-philosophy-of-stanislavski&#x2F;</link>
                <guid>http:&#x2F;&#x2F;lachlankermode.com&#x2F;performance-theory-alpha&#x2F;posts&#x2F;media-philosophy-of-stanislavski&#x2F;</guid>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Joseph Roach concisely summarizes the key theoretical frame of the method for which Stanislavski is famous:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Stanislavski System is a means of manipulating levels of consciousness to achieve certain specific effects on the body, especially the illusion of spontaneity. It promises to give the actor expressive control over a living organism, his own body, in all its mercurial diversity and surprising obstinancy…. Significantly, the implied division is not between body and mind, but between conscious and unconscious states.
                        The Player’s Passion: Studies in the Sciene of Acting, pp.206.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The body and mind (the latter sometimes referred to as the ‘soul’ in our Stanislavski translation) are not ontologically distinct, but rather are moments in the same psychosomatic materiality. Thoughts (mind) and physical reflexes (body) are coterminously subject to the same physics, produced by a dialectic of conscious and unconscious influence. Stanislavskian acting (“our type of art” pp.16, “our type of creativeness” pp.294) is the placement of a symbiotic construction within the topography of the actor’s unconscious, such that conscious mappings (thoughts and reflexes) takes that construction to be a part of the landscape. Though an actor’s performance is governed by the vast contours of the unconscious, the unconscious may be architected obliquely by a sustained conscious directive over time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though it is remarkable for the way it confounds classical mind&#x2F;body dualism, the metaphysical setup of Stanislavski’s actor is not surprising when one considers the theatre as medium. Roach’s suggestion that Stanislavski “sought to create a religion of art, in which the theatre was a temple, the audience worshippers, and the actors celebrants at a mysterious rite” pp.217 approaches this thinking, but one might go further and suggest the mediatic condition of the theatre as an allegorical and essentializing figure for understanding the System’s metaphysical ethics. Representation, not intention, is the ontological currency of the theatre. If something is not staged, it did not happen. Though the ethics of any given play is necessarily couched in codes and customs that carry from beyond the stage’s four walls, the ethics of the theatre-as-medium—that is, what makes a play ‘good’ or ‘bad’ unto itself—is always and only what can be experienced. In the theatre, if it is not on display, it is no good.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stanislavski’s method calls for the actor to submit himself&#x2F;herself entirely to the condition of theatre-as-medium. The role that is being played becomes ‘second nature’, and the everyday metaphysical condition (life-as-medium) is subsumed by that of the stage (theatre-as-medium). The changed metaphysical condition of the Stanislavskian actor is suggested throughout An Actor Prepares. It is, as Tortsov tells his pupils, “the state we call ‘I am’”[pp.273]. The state is consistently designated a “truth,” and is demonstratively achieved through the “miraculous metamorphosis”[pp.269] of Kostya in the final chapter. The first person narrator of the text, significantly the subjectivity who mediates the System for us as readers, dives into “the ocean of subconscious”[pp.274], gradually descending through different stages of mingled ontology (“The water is up to his waist now”[pp.274]). The ideal state is paradigmatically represented as the sea, perhaps the most powerful media-imaginary of an unbounded and unboundaried coalescence, in apposition to the territorialized terra firma. The Stanislavskian catharsis is so complete a submersion in the theatre-as-medium that its media politics are indistinguishable from its landlocked precedent: “my part and my own life were so intermingled that they seemed to merge”[pp.275].&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Roach suggests, Stanislavski’s permissive use of rhetorical flourish—“such sonorities as the ‘inner life of the human spirit’ rolled off his tongue far more naturally than technical terms like cerebral reflexes”[pp.217—lends towards a reading of the System as a religious rather than a scientific economy of terms. If his System is a religion, however, it is one with a chary attitude to the spiritual. The System is grounded first and foremost by nature, and only tangentially incorporates the ethereal. The actor must have absolute faith in the conceptual apparatus of the role, so as to wander firmly and confidently on deck the theatre’s ontological floorboards, but must never rely on the mystical intervention of inspiration to inflate the performance’s sails. There is on occasion a mystical sort of pathetic fallacy that punctuates an actor’s sea-faring; but inspiration is fickle Muse, and she “cannot be counted on”[pp.66] for every voyage.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-networked-actor-and-the-nautical-in-disney-s-moana&quot;&gt;THE NETWORKED ACTOR AND THE NAUTICAL IN DISNEY’S MOANA&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that we accept Stanislavski’s actor method in this way, namely as a nautical ethics of representation, I want to experimentally look at its (non)interplay with the technics and method of the modern animation pipeline. Narrative animation, such as that produced by Disney and Pixar, is an art of representation that superficially bears many similarities to the theatrical representation. Of course, it does nothing to misprize the history of criticism regarding medium specifity and claim that animation admits the same ethics as theatre—but neverthess, there is an interesting dialogue between the Stanislavski System for stage and the largely untheorized production methodology for animation. The condition of viewership in animated film still contains something of the ‘unbroken line’ and ‘super-objective’; might his methodology bear something on the many workers of the animation pipeline, the unglamorized collectivity that approximate the ‘actor’ in animation’s hippodrome?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ‘actor’ in anthropoidal animated films such as Disney’s Moana is no actor at all, but a 3D mesh that has been attributed with various layers, textures and other structured data to represent a character that has representational integrity from all possible perspectives. After this mesh has been constructed, the completion of the ‘modeling’ stage of the animation pipeline that often entails the work of 10s if not 100s of people in a complicated model, the mesh is passed to the ‘rigging’ specialists. Rigging is the process of structuring a virtual skeleton for the model, to restrict the possible spectra of deformations available to the animator, who will be handed the rigged model at the next stage of the pipeline. A sophisticated rigger will make clear the ‘natural’ movements of the character through a series of controls and digital restrictions put in place through the software being used, and will often also provide a ‘control panel’ that details clearly and protologically a character’s range of motion. Next the rigged model is given to the animators, who essentially specify the exact timing the model’s movements in virtual space through a range of techniques, usually engineering motion in accordance with a ‘script’ given by the director. Virtual cameras must also be timed and moved through virtual space to specify the perspective on each model and their virutal environs at any given time, with ‘cuts’ working conceptually in a very similar way to the production of a film using actual cameras and people.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</description>
            </item>
        <item>
                <title>The Knowledge Making of Ghosts</title>
                <pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>http:&#x2F;&#x2F;lachlankermode.com&#x2F;performance-theory-alpha&#x2F;posts&#x2F;knowledge-making-of-ghosts&#x2F;</link>
                <guid>http:&#x2F;&#x2F;lachlankermode.com&#x2F;performance-theory-alpha&#x2F;posts&#x2F;knowledge-making-of-ghosts&#x2F;</guid>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;      &lt;em&gt;I&#x27;ll have these players&lt;br&gt;
      Play something like the murder of my father&lt;br&gt;
      Before mine uncle: I&#x27;ll observe his looks;&lt;br&gt;
      I&#x27;ll tent him to the quick: if he but blench,&lt;br&gt;
      I know my course.&lt;br&gt;
                        Act II, Scene II.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamlet’s staging of The Mousetrap is an attempt to conjure a reaction from Claudius. The pithy end to Hamlet’s rendition of his plot’s purpose, “The play’s the thing wherein I’ll catch the conscience of the king,” conceals the intricate reasoning at work in what is arguably the play’s—Hamlet’s, that is—pivotal plot point; the staging of proof that Claudius is a murderous usurper.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening scene of Hamlet stages the appearance of a ghost. Marcellus and Bernando, the officers who first see the ghost walking the ramparts of Elsinore, summon their superior Horatio to reckon with the uncanny occurrence that so resembles the late king. They bid him speak to it, recognizing that he is “a scholar.” When the ghost fails to respond, Horatio gives his assessment:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;      &lt;em&gt;In what particular thought to work I know not;&lt;br&gt;
      But in the gross and scope of my opinion,&lt;br&gt;
      This bodes some strange eruption to our state.&lt;br&gt;
                        Act I, Scene I.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The state is indeed eventually erupted, all the royal family dying in some way or another by the play’s close. It is not only the political state, however, that flares up and out: the official knowledge-making praxis of courtly Elsinore inflects and implodes. Heralded, even ‘trumpeted,’ by the figure of the ghost, the state is refurbished in new epistemological dress. The body politic has been made volatile by its recently severed head, “the king that was and is the question of these wars,” and it is in such an unsettled state that the structures of officialism that upheld certain norms, traditions and customs (which might previously been [more] robust) collapse.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be legible is to be ‘clear enough to read,’ and, due to textuality’s enormous influence on our sense of what is legitimate, as per Conquergood, we use the word almost interchangeably with words like ‘understandable’ and ‘interpretable.’ Entwined with this is the preponderance of the visual in our epistemological constitution, as we are undoubtedly captive to one of Conquergood’s “dominant epistemologies that link knowing with seeing.”&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the role that seeing plays in our knowledge-making, the figure of the ghost represents that which should not be legible to a given epistemological configuration, but nevertheless is. The ghost is a category of phenomenon that blurs the distinction between binaries that cannot be confounded in an imaginary&#x2F;ideology, such as life and death. By doing so, the ghost exposes the fault lines of a given imaginary. The ghost is phenomenological evidence that a particular imaginary is not wholly sufficient to represent the Real.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shakespeare’s text pays lavish homage to this particular figure of ghost-as-exposê in many ways; perhaps most famously in Hamlet’s oft-quoted: “There are more things in heaven and earth, Horatio, than are dreamt of in your philosophy.” Horatio, the scholar, represents textuality’s grasp on the world. He is confounded when the ghost appears, having no imaginary in which the ghost can mean at all (quotation from top of page). Throughout much of the play, Hamlet functions as a sort of failed Socratic gadfly in this respect. He provokes the court of Elsinore to reconsider their knowledge-making praxis by dialogically exposing their language’s pretensions and presumptions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamlet’s staging of The Mousetrap is designed in light of a fact gleaned from a ghost. The mode of revelation through which Hamlet intends to prove this fact is a reaction to simulated events onstage by a band of players. A blameworthy Claudius, Hamlet assumes, will instinctually react, and crucially react visibly, to the dramatic reenactment of the usurping he has already performed, his complexion triggered by conscience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this sense, the play within a play in Hamlet represents a sophisticated rumination on ways of knowing, and in particular the ways in which historical or factual knowing interplay with both ghostly knowing (hauntology) and theatrical knowing (I’m sure there’s a theorist who has a word here, but I might suggest ‘histrionography’). The tension between factual knowing. What is factually known is that which is legible through the dominant modes of knowing in an epistemological frame. The contemporary mode of knowing, both our’s and Shakespeare’s, as I have suggested through Conquergood, is characterized by its textual and visual strands—though admittedly Shakespeare’s relationship to verbal&#x2F;aural knowing is likely quite different than our own ratiocinative, data-driven thinking, given the 16th century’s antediluvian landscapes of literacy and technological medium.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to its readability in the official death toll of the state, the eruption of the Denmark state is also performantly (invoking Diana Taylor and her preference for this term over the already-canonized ‘performative’) inscribed in the dialogic contours of Hamlet’s “crafty madness.” Through a combination of his already-legible status as prince and artful ingenuity, Hamlet serves as an attorney for those subjugated modes of knowledge, hauntology and historionography, in Elsinore’s court. This advocacy is spelled out in Hamlet’s reflections immediately after his first encounter with the ghost:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;      &lt;em&gt;Yea, from the table of my memory&lt;br&gt;
      I’ll wipe away all trivial fond records,&lt;br&gt;
      All saws of books, all forms, all pressures past,&lt;br&gt;
      That youth and observation copied there;&lt;br&gt;
      And thy commandment all alone shall live&lt;br&gt;
      Within the book and volume of my brain,&lt;br&gt;
      Unmix’d with baser matter: yes, by heaven!&lt;br&gt;
                        Act I, Scene V.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamlet unravels the state by putting pressure on those of its epistemological tendencies that do not hold up to phenomenological scrutiny, by playing the protagonist who gives weight to the words of ghosts. He becomes cognizant of the mnemonic erasures that the archive purports, and tunes his knowledge-making to do justice to what he sees as effaced. His characted is not staged, however, entirely as an embodiment of Diana Taylor’s repertoire, those mnemonic practices that belie the archive. He is more of an epistemlogical imp, a messenger between ghosts and offical bodies that mischeviously meddles with expected corollaries to their eventual implosion. Hamlet does not destroy the letter that orders his execution; he rewrites it to condemn Rosencrantz and Guildernstern (the existential happening that inspires Tom Stoppard’s famous play).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To return, on this note, to the figure of a play within a play: Shakespeare’s attention to the intricate epistemological theatre of his own knowledge-making practice Is iterated throughout Hamlet, but The Mousetrap is perhaps its most concisely performed profile. Ingeniously, Shakespeare inductively legitimates theatre-as-medium by staging the play as the pivot through which hauntology influences the dominant modes of knowledge. Claudius’ reaction is that of one who, retreating to the comfort of familiar optic sensibility, will not bear witness to ghosts: “Give me some light, away!” The courtly (Greek) chorus emphatically echoes his sentiment triadically, a performative call that bids all leave but those who have seen and believed a ghost earlier in the play, Hamlet and Horatio.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</description>
            </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
